So now you can take off your shoes comfortably
सो अब आपको जूते उते उतार ले आराम से जो
People sitting on chairs, also remove their shoes
लोग कुर्सियों पर बैठे वह भी जूते उतार के
keep two feet apart, those who are sitting on the ground
दोनों पैर अलग कर रहे जो जमीन पर बैठे हैं
That's the best.
वो सबसे ठीक है।
[Music]
[संगीत]
OK, now remember my three conditions
ठीक अब मेरी तीन शर्त याद रखें
and don't forget them.
वो भूलनी नहीं
Now, first of all, we will
अब सबसे पहले आपको हम
show you how you can
दिखाएंगे के किस तरह से आप अपनी कुंडली
awaken your Kundali
जागृत करेंगे
In what way
किस तरह से अब ये
So now I am also showing it to you
आपको दिखा देंगे और हम भी आपको बता
and I am also telling you that our
रहे हैं कि अपना लेफ्ट हैंड जो है
left hand toward me
लेफ्ट हैंड उसको हमारी ओर करें।
now left hand, is left side
अब लेफ्ट हैंड में लेफ्ट साइड
is the power of desire
में जो शक्ति है वो इच्छा शक्ति
power of desire
पावर ऑफ डिजायर, इच्छा शक्ति जब आपने
when you put your hands like this, it means
ऐसे हाथ कर दिया तो
.
.
You have said, I wish that
आपने यह कह दिया है कि हमें इच्छा है कि
Mother gives me Self-realization
मां हमें आत्म साक्षात्कार मिले
Keep it like this all the time and the right hand
इसको पूरी समय ऐसा रखें और राइट हैंड
is the power of action, with this we can fix our chakras.
जो है
is the power of action, That's how we get our
यह क्रिया शक्ति है इसी से हम अपने
energy centres corrected
चक्रों को ठीक करेंगे
So first of all we should place our right hand
तो सबसे पहले राइट हैंड हम अपने
on our heart.
हृदय पर रखें
I told you about the spirit is the heart
मैंने आपसे बताया हृदय में आत्मा का
is the refelction
प्रतिबिंब है
After that we place our hand
उसके बाद हम अपना
on the upper part of the stomach
हाथ पेट के ऊपरी हिस्से में रखेंगे।
we keep working on our work left side,
सब काम हम लेफ्ट साइड में कर रहे हैं
this is the place of our Guru
यह हमारी गुरु का स्थान है
-
_
Meaning, the great teachers have
माने बड़े-बड़े जो सदगुरु हो गए उन्होंने
created this Chakra for us and
हमारे लिए यह चक्र बनाया हुआ है और इसकी
by it awakening , you become your own Guru.
जागृति से आप अपने गुरु हो जाते हैं
Then place your hand on the lower part
फिर अपना हाथ पेट के नीच
of your stomach,
हिस्से में रखें
left hand side
लेफ्ट हैंड साइड
Then take this
फिर यही
hand up and again
हाथ ऊपर ले जाए फिर
to the left hand side
से लेफ्ट हैंड साइड में
Place it in the upper abdomen,
अपने पेट
(stomach area)
के ऊपरी हिस्से में रखें
Now again over the heart
फिर से हृदय पर रखें
Now place your hand at the angle
अब यह हाथ अपनी गर्दन और अपना कंधा
between your neck and your shoulder
इसके बीच के कोण के ऊपर रखें
Keep the angle as far back as you can
कोण में जहां तक पीछे जा सकता है
and turn the neck to the right side
और गर्दन को राइट साइड में मोड़ ले
I just told you when this centre
मैंने आपसे अभी बताया कि यह चक्र
get caught up,and what diseases occurs.
पकड़ने से क्या बीमारियां हो जाती हैं।
Now, hold your right hand completely.
अब अपने हाथ को राइट हैंड को पूरी
in a horizontal position like this
तरह से आड़ा इस तरह से अपने माथे पर रख
on your forehead
कपाल पर
and bend your neck down fully.
और पूरी तरह से गर्दन नीचे झुका ले
This
यह
centre
चक्र
is to forgive all.
हमें सबको एक साथ माफ करने के लिए है।
Now place your right hand on the back of
अब अपना राइट हैंड सर के पीछे के हिस्से
your head
में डालें
and turn your head backwards,
और सर को पीछे की ओर मोड़ दे,
as far as you can
जहां तक मोड़ सकते हैं।
Here
इस जगह
by not blaming yourself,
अपने को दोषी ना ठहराते हुए
and not counting your mistakes
अपनी गलतियां ना गिनते हुए
For your own satisfaction you should say,
अपने ही समाधान के लिए आपको कहना चाहिए
O God, If I have made a mistakes please forgive me',
कि 'हे परम चैतन्य हमसे कोई गलती हुई तो क्षमा करो'
this will happen later,
यह बाद में होगा अभी आप जान लीजिए
These centre is for this purpose.
ये चक्र इसी कार्य के लिए है।
Now open your hand fully,
अब अपना हाथ पूरी तरह से फैला दीजिए
and the middle part of the palm should be evenly
और हथेली के बीच का हिस्सा  बराबर
placed on the palate of your head
आपके सर के तालू के ऊपर रखा जाए
-
-
And
और
it is very important, to pull your fingers out to press it completely
उसे पूरी तरह से दबाने के लिए उंगलियां
It is very important to pull it out and
बाहर की ओर खींच ले बहुत जरूरी है
place in on the palate of the head and fingers pointing outwards
तालू पर रखा जाए और उंगलिया बाहर की ओर
Pull out completely and
पूरी तरह खींच ले और सर को पूरी तरह से
bow down your head completely
नीचे झुका ले
-
-
Now you put full pressure
अब आप अपने हाथ को
of your hand
पूरा दबाव डालकर के
Rotate it in this way
इस तरह से घुमाएं
on the scalp of your head
आपके सर की जो स्कल्प है चमड़ी है
It will rotate
वह घूमेगी
like the hands of a clock
घड़ी के कांटे जैसे
Rotate it in the same direction as the hands of a clock
उस दिशा से घुमाइए जैसे घड़ी के कांटे घूमते हैं
7 times; done;
7 मर्तबा; हो गया;
That's all you have to do, now
इतना ही बस करना है, अब आपके पास
If you have glasses then take them out because now
चश्मा शमा हो तो निकाल लीजिए क्योंकि अब
You have to close your eyes and if something is tight
आंखें बंद करनी है और पेट पर अगर कुछ चीज
on your stomach or neck then
तंग हो या गर्दन में तो उसे भी जरा
loosen it a little.
कम करले
And everybody
और सब लोग इसे
should do it fully
करें पूरी तरह से
Again I repeat, with pleasent mind
फिर से मैं कहूंगी कि प्रसन्न चित्त
do it
हो जाए
Now close your eyes and do not open any of them.
अब आप आंखें बंद कर ले कोई भी आंख ना खोले
Close your eyes and
आंख बंद कर ले
put your hand on your heart.
और अपना हाथ हृदय पर रखें
Now ask a question to yourself in your heart
अब एक प्रश्न आप अपने मन में
ask me
मेरे लिए  पूछे
You may call me Shri Mataji,
मुझे आप श्री माता जी कहे,
Or say Mother
या चाहे मां कहे
You ask the question
आप प्रश्न पूछिए
Mother, am I the spirit?' ask the question three times
मां क्या मैं आत्मा हूं ' तीन बार प्रश्न
Ask
पूछे
This is a very basic question.
यह बड़ा मूलभूत प्रश्न है
Now you
अब आप
must know that if you the pure spirit, then you
यह जान लीजिए कि अगर आप आत्मा हो गए तो आप
also become your own Guru
अपने गुरु भी हो जाते हैं
Because in the light of your spirit
क्योंकि आत्मा के प्रकाश में
you become
आप अपने
your own Guru, so please put your
ही गुरु हो जाते हैं इसलिए आप कृपया अपना
right hand on the upper part of the stomach
राइट हैंड पेट के ऊपरी हिस्से में रखें
the left hand on the side
लेफ्ट हैंड साइड पर
Press it with your fingers.
उंगलियों से दबा लें।
these guru principle;
इस गुरु तत्व को;
music
[संगीत]
Now ask me the second question here
अब यहां दूसरा प्रश्न मुझसे करें
Mother, am I my own Guru?'
' मां क्या मैं स्वयं का गुरु हूं  '
Mother, am I my own guru?'
मां क्या मैं अपना ही गुरु हूं  '
Am I my own master?
क्या मैं अपना ही मास्टर हूं '
Ask me these question three times
यह सवाल आप मुझसे तीन बार पूछिए
In your mind
अपने मन में
Now you put your right hand
अब आप अपना राइट हैंड
on the lower part of the stomach, on your
पेट के निचले हिस्से में लेफ्ट हैंड
Left side
साइड में
put
रखें
And know that
और यह जान लीजिए
I respect your freedom
कि मैं आपकी स्वतंत्रता
fully.
का पूर्ण आदर करती हूं
And I cannot force these
और आप पर मैं
pure knowledge upon you
जबरदस्ती शुद्ध विद्या लाद नहीं सकती
The pure knowledge
जो शुद्ध विद्या
from this Chakra will give you
इस चक्र से आपको
complete knowledge of the power of God
पूरा ज्ञान कराएगी परमात्मा की शक्ति का
So here you have to say
इसलिए आपको यहां
this six times
कहना होगा छह मर्तबा
because this chakra has six petals.
क्योंकि इस चक्र में छह पंखुड़िया है
You have to ask in your heart
अपने हृदय में आपको मांगना होगा
Shri Mataji please give me pure knowledge'
श्री माता जी मुझे आप शुद्ध विद्या
-
दीजिए
Now
अब
You press your
आप अपना
hands a little harder
हाथ जरा जोर से दबाए
As soon as you ask for pure knowledge,
जैसे ही आप शुद्ध विद्या मांगते हैं वैसे ही
the awakening of Kundalini begins
कुंडलिनी का जागरण शुरू हो
-
गया
But for that we will have to
लेकिन उसके लिए ऊपर के जो चक्र है उन्हें
open the upper chakras.
हमें खोल देना होगा
Now raise your right hand and place it on your stomach.
आप अपना राइट हैंड अब उठा कर के पेट के
Keep it in the upper left side
ऊपरी हिस्से में लेफ्ट साइड में रखें
and with full confidence
और पूर्ण आत्मविश्वास के साथ
The chakras will open only with confidence
आत्मविश्वास से ही चक्र खुलेंगे
With full confidence you say
पूर्ण आत्मविश्वास के साथ आप कहे
Mother
श्री माता जी
I am my own Guru'
मैं स्वयं का गुरु हूं '
With full confidence say
पूर्ण आत्मविश्वास के साथ
10 times
कए 10 मर्तबा
say it 10 times
कहिए 10 टाइम्स
I have already told you
आपसे मैंने पहले ही
that you are a spirit.
बताया कि आप आत्मा है
You are not a body, intellect, mind, ego, etc.
आप शरीर बुद्धि मन अहंकारा आदि उपाधि नहीं है
But you are a pure spirit
किंतु आप शुद्ध आत्मा है
Now place your right hand on your heart
अब अपना राइट हैंड आप हृदय पर रखें
And with full faith
और पूर्ण विश्वास के साथ
say this 12 times
आप 12 मर्तबा कहिए
Shri Mataji
श्री माता जी
I am a pure spirit
मैं शुद्ध आत्मा हूं
Mother, I am a pure spirit
श्री माता जी मैं शुद्ध आत्मा हूं
Say it in your own language, in whatever language
अपनी अपनी भाषा में कहिए जिस भाषा में
you want to say it,
कहना चाहे
say it 12 times
12 मर्तबा कहिए
Now I will say one thing again that
अब एक बात फिर से कहूंगी कि
you are not guilty, you are not a sinner
आप दोषी नहीं है आप पापी नहीं है
do not bring down yourself to the lowest level
आप अपने को न्यूनता में ना उतार
You are human
आप मानव है
and you are glorious
और गौरवशाली है
This love of God is spread all around
चारों तरफ फैला हुआ परमात्मा का यह प्यार
he is the ocean of forgiveness
ये समुद्र है क्षमा का आप
We can't make any mistake that
कोई ऐसी गलती नहीं कर सकते कि
this ocean
जो इस समुद्र में पूरी
cannot destroy
तरह नष्ट ना हो जाए
So forgive yourself and
इसलिए आप अपने ही को क्षमा करें और
your right hand
अपना राइट हैंड
between your shoulder and your neck
अपना कंधा और अपनी गर्दन इसके
in the middle
बीचोबीच रखें
And turn your neck completely to the right side
और अपनी गर्दन राइट साइड को पूरी तरह
turn it
से मोड़ दे
Here
यहां पर
you have to say 16 times
आपको 16 मर्तबा कहना होगा
Mother, I am not guilty at all '
श्री माता जी मैं बिल्कुल दोषी नहीं हूं
I am innocent say it 16 times with full
मैं निर्दोष हूं 16 मर्तबा कए पूर्ण
Say with faith I say that
विश्वास के साथ कहिए मैं कहती हूं कि
You are innocent
आप निर्दोष है
say it again, if you forgive others
फिर से यही कहना है कि आप किसी को क्षमा करें
you don't do anything
या ना करें आप कुछ नहीं करते पर अगर
If you do not forgive, you play in
आप क्षमा नहीं करते हैं तो आप गलत हाथों
wrong hands
में खेलते हैं
therfore
इसलिए
Forgive all of them together, your
आप सबको एक साथ क्षमा करें अपना हाथ
right hand
राइट हैंड
Place it horizontally across your forehead
अपने माथे पर अपने कपाल पर आड़ा रखें
Press on both sides and bend your neck down
दबाएं  दोनों साइड में नीचे गर्तन झुका ले
And here
और यहां पर
I say it with full confidence
पूर्ण आत्मविश्वास से कहे
Mother, I have forgiven all, together
श्री माता जी मैंने सबको एक साथ क्षमा कर
-
_
I, together
मैंने सबको एक साथ
forgiven all together
क्षमा कर दिया
how many times you say, not important
कितने बार कहने की बात नहीं
must say it from the heart
हृदय से कहना होगा
Mother, I forgiven everyone.
मां मैंने सबको एक साथ क्षमा कर दिया
Now take your right hand back
अब राइट हैंड को पीछे ले
and
और
bend your head back
अपने सर पीछे की ओर झुका
This is the place
इस जगह
For your satisfaction
अपने समाधान के लिए
without blaming yourself or counting your mistakes
अपनी गलतियां ना गिनते हुए अपने को दोषी
for your own satisfaction
न ठहराते हुए अपने ही समाधान के लिए
You have to say it with your heart
आपको कहना होगा हृदय के साथ
-
-
O God, if I have committed any mistake
हे परम चैतन्य हमारे हाथ से अगर कोई गलती हुई हो
knowingly or unknowingly, please forgive me
जाने अनजाने तो कृपया माफ कर दीजिए
Say this from your heart, it is does not a matter
यह भी हृदय से कहे कितने बार कहने
how many times you say it
की बात नहीं
Now the last chakra is very important
अब आखिरी चक्र म बहुत महत्त्वपूर्ण है
Keep your left hand and both feet apart
लेफ्ट हैंड हमारे और रखें दोनों पैर
those who are sitting on the floor, should remain seated comfortably,
अलग रखें जो नीचे बैठे हैं वह आराम से
but now spread their hands properly
बैठे रहे लेकिन अब अपने हाथ को पसार ले
Stretch your palm fully, and then
हथेली को पूरी तरह से खींच ले और उसके
in the middle,
बीचोबीच
the area
जो जगह
you should put it on your palate, which is your
है उसको आप बराबर अपने तालू पर जो कि आपके
In my childhood, had a very soft bone (fontenel bone)
बचपन में एक बहुत स्निग्ध सी हड्डी थी
Place it on it
उस पर रखें
and bend your neck completely
और अपनी गर्दन झुका ले पूरी तरह
open your fingers, completely
से अपनी उंगलियों को पूरी तरह से कीजिए
stretch it outward
बाहर की ओर इससे पूरा दबाव
on your scalp and on the skin
आपके स्कल्प पर आपके सर की चमड़ी पर
of your scalp
पड़े
Now know that
अब यह जान
-
लीजिए कि मैं
I respect your freedom
स्वतंत्रता को मानती हूं
And I can't force self-realization on you.
और मैं आप पर आत्म साक्षात्कार लाद नहीं सकती
Now you have to ask
आपको मांगना होगा अब
Please move this hand slowly seven times
कृपया इस हाथ को आप सात मर्तबा धीरे
Clockwise means slowly like the hands of a clock
क्लॉक वाइज माने घड़ी के कांटे की तरह धीरे-धीरे
Rotate and say Mother, seven times
घुमाए और कहे सात मर्तबा श्री माता जी
Please give me my self realization'
मुझे आप कृपया आत्म साक्षात्कार द
Please give me self realization Mother, please give me self realization
मुझे आत्म बोध दीजिए श्री माता जी मुझे आप आत्म
Realization
बोध दीज
do it seven times
सात मर्तबा कर
[music]
[संगीत]
Now slowly turn your eyes
अब धीरे-धीरे अपनी आंखें
Now turn both your hands towards me like this
अब दोनों हाथ मेरी और करें इस तरह से
And look at me
और मेरी ओर देखें
And become thoughtless
और निर्विचार हो जाए
Don't think
विचार मत करें
Now move your right hand a little forward and bow your head
अब राइट हैंड थोड़ा आगे करके अपना सर झुका के
See if there is any cool or warm air coming from
देखें  कि आपके ताल में से ठंडी या गरम गरम
above your head
कुछ हवा आ रही है क्या सर के ऊपर
put your hand, don't touch it, feel it from far
हाथ रखें उसको छुए नहीं दूर से देखें
For some,the breeze comes from quiet far
किसी किसी को बहुत दूर तक आती है हवा
See the cold breeze coming from your head?
आ रही ठंडी हवा, देखिए सर में से आ रही है
put your right hand towards me, your right hand,
राइट हैंड मेरी ओर करिए राइट हैंड,
check with your left hand, first your right hand
लेफ्ट हैंड से देख,  पहले राइट हैंड
towards me, now with your left hand
करें मेरी ओर अब लेफ्ट हैंड से
right hand toward me and do it and check with your left hand
राइट हैंड मेरे और करें लेफ्ट हैंड से
Look, is it's coming, on your left hand
देखिए आ रही अच्छा अब लेफ्ट हैंड
Now bend your neck and check with your right hand
मेरे अब गर्दन झुका के देखि राइट हैंड से
is is coming? everybody check
आ रही क्या ? देखि सब आ रही
ask me a question, Mother,
एक सवाल पूछे कि श्री माता जी क्या
is this the supreme consciousness?
यही परम चैतन्य है?
Is this the power of God's love?
यही क्या परमात्मा की प्रेम शक्ति है
Ask any one of question three times
तीन बार कोई सा भी एक प्रश्न करें
push your neck up toward the sky
ऊपर गर्दन करके आकाश की ओर देखें
bring it down
नीचे ले लीजिए
keep your hands like this
हाथ ऐसे रखें आप
All those people ,
जिन लोगों
who feel cold or hot air coming from top of the head or the palm or fingers
के तालू से या हाथ में उंगलियों में
All those people put your hand
ठंडी या गर्म हवा आ रही हो वह सब लोग हाथ
put up,
ऊपर करें
whole of Hyderabad has got realised
पूरा हैदराबाद ही पार हो गया सबको
Salutations to you, salutations to all the saints,
आपको नमस्कार सब संतों को नमस्कार अनंत
Infinite Blessings
आशीर्वाद